"How the Dairy Industry
Designs Misleading Studies"
Observational studies like these,
suggesting dairy might not be so bad,
can be confounded by extraneous
factors, such as the fact that people
who eat more cheese tend to be
of higher socioeconomic class.
Fine, but what about
this interventional study?
A randomized, crossover trial which
compared a high-fat cheese diet,
to a high-fat meat diet,
to a low-fat diet.
A high cheese diet: CHEESE,
which is loaded with saturated fat,
a high meat diet: MEAT, which
is loaded with saturated fat,
versus CARB, a low-fat diet,
and people ended up with
the same cholesterol levels.
Let's see how they did it.
Half the study was paid for
in part by the dairy industry,
and the other half paid for by
dairy, dairy, dairy, and dairy.
If you're the dairy industry, and
you're trying to design a study
to show that a high cheese diet
doesn't raise cholesterol,
how would you go
about doing that?
Anyone remember this video?
It's one of my favorites.
The beef industry was in the
same pickle as the cheese industry.
Beef has saturated fat,
which raises cholesterol,
which raises the risk of
dying from our #1 killer.
What's an industry to do?
So they designed a study where they
added beef, and cholesterols went down.
How is that possible?
Here's the two diets.
They added beef and the
cholesterols went down.
They did this by cutting out so much
dairy, pork, poultry, fish, and eggs
that their overall saturated
fat intake was cut in half.
They cut saturated fat levels in half
and the cholesterol levels went down.
Well, duh.
They could
have swapped in Twinkies
and said snack cakes lower your
cholesterol, or frosting or anything.
OK, so now that
you know the trick,
let's go back to this study.
How are you going to get
a high-fat cheese diet,
and a high-fat meat diet
to have anywhere near the
same saturated fat level
as a diet with neither, unless...
Wait, don't tell me.
What, they added coconut oil
or something to the other diet?
They added so much
coconut oil and cookies
to the so-called low fat diet
that they were able to sufficiently
raise the level of saturated fat
to cause a similar
rise in cholesterol.
That's now you can make sure
a cheese or meat-rich diet
look like it doesn't
raise cholesterol.
That reminds me of the desperation
evident in this study
that compared the effects
of dairy cheddar cheese to a nondairy
cheddar cheese called Daiya.
Milk consumption has
plummeted in recent years
as people have discovered
plant-based alternatives
like soymilk and almond milk,
and now there's plant-based
cheese alternatives?
What's the National Dairy Council to do?
How are you going to design a study
that shows it's healthier to eat cheese,
design a study where cheese causes less
inflammation than the vegan alternative?
They got their work
cut out for them.
Daiya is no health
food by any stretch,
but definitely three times less
saturated fat than cow cheese.
So, I give up.
How could you possibly show
more inflammation from Daiya?
Well, there is one fat that may cause
more inflammation that milk fat: palm oil.
In fact, it may raise
cholesterol levels
as much as trans-fat laden
partially hydrogenated oil.
Yeah, but what, are you telling me
they like slipped the Daiya group
some extra palm oil on the side?
Yes, can you believe it?
They compared cheese
to Daiya plus palm oil,
so much extra palm oil that the
vegan alternative meal ended up
having the same amount of
saturated fat as the cheese meal.
That's like proving tofu is worse
than beef by doing a study
where they compared a beef burger
to a tofu patty stuffed with lard.
Oh, wait, the meat industry
already did that, but at least
they had the decency to concede
that replacement of meat
by tofu in the habitual diet
would probably not usually be
accompanied by the addition of lard.